If you took some of the biggest and most
famous diamonds in the world and smashed
them open, you'd find evidence that they
come from way deeper than you think. Way
deeper than other diamonds. As you drill
into the earth, as pressure and
temperature change, that means that the
minerals that you're passing change,
too. Up here, you'll find where most
other gemstones form, but keep going.
You're entering the mantle. It's getting
hotter and the pressure around you is
getting stronger, and down here is where
most diamonds form. And if we're lucky,
the surrounding minerals get trapped
inside diamonds when they form. But big
famous diamonds are often so pure that
those inclusions are too small to
analyze, or there aren't any. So,
scientists turned to smaller less
perfect specimens pulled from the same
place in the earth that do have larger
inclusions. And they realized that these
inclusions have a rare mixture of
elements that can only be created with
extreme pressure found here, way deeper
than other diamonds. So, they created a
new category for these gems called
superdeep diamonds. But now, we can
actually grow diamonds in a totally new
way. To see that, subscribe.